<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Devs on Acid</title>
<link>https://sabotage-linux.github.io</link>
<description>Random rants of a linux distribution developer</description>
<language>en</language>
<item><title>the rusty browser trap</title>
<guid>https://sabotage-linux.github.io/blog/3</guid>
<pubDate>06 Apr 2019 11:55 UTC</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
<p>If you're following <a href="https://github.com/sabotage-linux/sabotage/">sabotage linux</a>
development, you may have noticed that we're stuck on Firefox 52esr, which was
released over a year ago.
This is because non-optional parts of Firefox were rewritten in the "Rust"
programming language, and all newer versions now require to have a Rust compiler
installed.</p>

<h4>And that is a real problem.</h4>

<p>The Rust compiler is written in Rust itself, exposing the typical hen-and-egg
problem.
Its developers have used previous releases in binary form along the path of
evolution of the language and its compiler. This means in practice that one can
only build a rust compiler by using a binary build supplied by a third party,
...</p>
]]></description></item>
<item><title>how compatible is libreSSL ?</title>
<guid>https://sabotage-linux.github.io/blog/2</guid>
<pubDate>12 Jul 2014</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
<h4>portability</h4>

<p>yesterday the "portable" version of libressl was released.
http://ftp.openbsd.org/pub/OpenBSD/LibreSSL/libressl-2.0.0.tar.gz</p>

<p>i set up a package in <a href="https://github.com/sabotage-linux/sabotage">sabotage linux</a>,
and went on a voyage to investigate whether the full set of packages can be
used with libressl instead of openssl.</p>

<p>first of all, i had to fight some obstacles to get libressl compiling though...</p>

<h5>obstacle 1 - -Werror</h5>

<p>...</p>
]]></description></item>
<item><title>sqlite's anal gamation</title>
<guid>https://sabotage-linux.github.io/blog/1</guid>
<pubDate>25 Sep 2013</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
<p>sqlite's slogan: <strong>"Small. Fast. Reliable. Choose any three."</strong></p>

<p>i always wondered though, how such a small or "lite" package can take such a
considerable amount of time to build.</p>

<p>as the main author of the sabotage linux distribution, building software is my
daily bread, so i own a pretty fast build box.
it's an 8 core machine with 3.1 GHz, which builds a complete 3.11 linux kernel
in less than 5 minutes, making use of all 8 cores via the nice parallel build
feature of GNU make.</p>

<pre><code>make -j8
</code></pre>

<p>when invoking make like this, it first determines the dependencies between the
...</p>
]]></description></item>
</channel></rss>
